<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Franchising | David Rickmann</title>
    <link>/tags/franchising/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/franchising/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Franchising</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Franchising</title>
      <link>/tags/franchising/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>GWR Direct Award 3</title>
      <link>/project/gwr_da3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/gwr_da3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The GWR Franchise was due to expire March 2020. In november 2017 the Department for Transport made the decision to extend their franchise until April 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I joined the team in 2019  where I acted as a n expert in rail performance modelling. My role was to advise the existing Performance team as they underwent a forensic examination of the bid comparator model during negotiations between the department for transport and first group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked primarily to help the team understand the model drivers and causes from a high level view, and from there went on to advise on suitable benchmark and payment rate regimes for the franchise direct award.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Southeastern DAC4</title>
      <link>/project/southeastern_dac4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/southeastern_dac4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In June 2017 the Department for Transport announced a shortlist of bidders to take over the southeastern franchise. There were several problems with available bidders leading to the postponement of the franchise bidding process. To resolve this issue in the short term the Department for Transport extended the existing franchise until ultimately the franchise competition was cancelled. The Department for Transport chose to further extend the current franchise agreement until 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I joined the Direct Award team in late 2019, advising the department on suitable benchmark and payment rate regimes for the franchise direct award. Due to the tight timescales a traditional performance model was not developed, instead aspects of the original competition franchise were rolled forward and adapted to be applied to the new contract.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wales and Borders Franchise Bid</title>
      <link>/project/wales-bid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/wales-bid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In October 2016 Transport for Wales began a procurement process for a operational and delivery partner for the Wales and Borders transformation project. This project was to deliver a £5 billion investment in transforming the Wales and Borders rail franchise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working with Keolis/Amey I led the performance modelling effort, developing the performance model and advising the performance team on all regulatory aspects of the bid process.
This franchise was the first to be offered by the newly Transport For Wales, requiring a cross border solution integrating modelling of Welsh and English rail services, as well as working on processes for dealing with large sections of infrastructure which was to be transferred to the new infrastructure manager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After we had succesfully won the bid I worked with the newly formed &amp;ldquo;Transport For Wales&amp;rdquo; branded franchise helped develop their operational capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
