<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | David Rickmann</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Horizon Innovations Study</title>
      <link>/project/horizon-innovations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/horizon-innovations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Horizon Innovations study was an examination of upcoming technical innovations with the aim of determining which areas of legislation the department should focus on to encourage the development of innovations in the field. David&amp;rsquo;s role was data scientists, conducting data cleaning, sorting and topic modelling to better understand which fields the included innovations were in, how they were distributed and which fields were most amenable to legislative intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wales and Borders Franchise Bid</title>
      <link>/project/wales-bid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/wales-bid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was the performance modelling lead on the winning bid for the Wales and Borders franchise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HS2 Health and safety analysis.</title>
      <link>/project/hs2-h_and_s/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/hs2-h_and_s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to reduce work related injuries the High Speed 2 project undertook an analysis of health and safety data sourced from the Crossrail project, with the assumption that two large rail projects would have similar risk factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I led a team of 4 analysts conducting a deep dive into all aspects of safety related incidents over the lifetime of Crossrail. We deliberately adopted a naive stance, rejecting standard assumptions of health and safety until they could be compared against the corpus of data available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amongst the findings we discovered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No evidence that clocks changing was a significant factor for workplace injury.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A limited impact of &amp;ldquo;Toolbox talks&amp;rdquo; or safety briefings with a detrimental effect at higher frequency (presumed due to complacency)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No increased injuries during snow days, but an increased injury rate approximately one week after snowy weather. Presumed to be caused by an increase in caution during the snowy weather, since the hazard it presents is evident, but a reduced level of caution once that risk and resultant risk controls are removed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
