<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | David Rickmann</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Horizon Innovations Study</title>
      <link>/project/horizon-innovations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/horizon-innovations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Horizon Innovations study was an examination of upcoming technical innovations with the aim of determining which areas of legislation the department should focus on to encourage the development of innovations in the field. David&amp;rsquo;s role was data scientists, conducting data cleaning, sorting and topic modelling to better understand which fields the included innovations were in, how they were distributed and which fields were most amenable to legislative intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative Volume of Childern and Pigeons</title>
      <link>/project/pigeons/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/pigeons/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was asked to undertake this study by a neighbourhood child who wanted to know how many uncompressed pigeons would occupy the same space as a five year old child. I advised the client on the principle of &amp;ldquo;Wisdom of the Crowd&amp;rdquo; as first demonstrated by Francis Galton whereby multiple independant observations tended to converge on a more accurate answer than any of those individual observations. They then conducted a survey to determine an estimated answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The client was concerned that their respondees were insufficiently motivated and / or knowledgable within the study domain and requested a more involved supplementary analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My analysis began with stating known variables (The specific characteristics of the subject child) and then a follow up desk based material review. From this review data sources for average child heights and weights was aquired along with average mass and body density data for various bird species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The  General Linear Models procedure (SAS Institute. Inc. 1988) was used to determine differences in density and feather mass among species and between sexes within species. Because the use of two or more related response variables (i.e. three measurements of density) to address a single hypothesis increases the probability of committing a type I error, the Bonferroni inequality technique was employed to ensure that the type I error rate was  under .05 (Bed &amp;amp; Khamis 1991). To maintain this probability level, 0.05 was divided by the number of response variables (three) tested. resulting in significant differences at P &amp;lt; 0.017. If differences occurred. Tukey tests were used to determine which means differed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From these data sources I was able to determine the average volume of a five year old child to be 34 pigeons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final report was delivered to the client who reported a high level of satisfaction with the finished work. This report is available from the PDF link above.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wales and Borders Franchise Bid</title>
      <link>/project/wales-bid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/wales-bid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was the performance modelling lead on the winning bid for the Wales and Borders franchise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HS2 Health and safety analysis.</title>
      <link>/project/hs2-h_and_s/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/hs2-h_and_s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to reduce work related injuries the High Speed 2 project undertook an analysis of health and safety data sourced from the Crossrail project, with the assumption that two large rail projects would have similar risk factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I led a team of 4 analysts conducting a deep dive into all aspects of safety related incidents over the lifetime of Crossrail. We deliberately adopted a naive stance, rejecting standard assumptions of health and safety until they could be compared against the corpus of data available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amongst the findings we discovered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No evidence that clocks changing was a significant factor for workplace injury.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A limited impact of &amp;ldquo;Toolbox talks&amp;rdquo; or safety briefings with a detrimental effect at higher frequency (presumed due to complacency)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No increased injuries during snow days, but an increased injury rate approximately one week after snowy weather. Presumed to be caused by an increase in caution during the snowy weather, since the hazard it presents is evident, but a reduced level of caution once that risk and resultant risk controls are removed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
